{
  "reference_number": "10077",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Without a clear target and timeframe, it is likely that government will avoid setting definitive policy in a positive way on the matter. We\n need government and policy makers to be strong on the issue and set policies that will encourage businesses to innovate and\n\n challenge the status quo."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "I believe the other options are complex and difficult to easily explain to the electorate. I also believe that we should be innovating. As\n pointed out during the discussions with businesses, other countries will find themselves with this pattern of emission later in the\n century and we would be ahead of the curve in terms of ways to measure and combat methane emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Although overseas emissions have a clear cost benefit, I believe that New Zealand should use this opportunity to invest in New\n\n Zealand and replenish some of the native woodland that we have lost over the years."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I believe that the only circumstance that the bill should be allowed to be changed is to make it faster. I.e. to get to zero carbon before\n 2050. I understand the argument around natural disasters and one off events, however, I believe it is potentially harmful to progress\n\n to think about this now. I don't think those decision should be made or conceived until/unless they happen. Although, we may have a\n natural disaster or event, it may be sufficiently close to 2050 that it doesn't disrupt our path to obtaining net zero carbon."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the budgets should not be in line with government cycles and should fall outside of that."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "My concern is that we will make some good gains in the early years (low hanging fruit) but subsequent to that low hanging fruit, it will\n become more challenging. So, my concern is that the first few budgets may be easily met and therefore the budget will be easy. I\n would only want to change the budget to make it more challenging for governments to meet, to encourage and promote continuous\n\n improvement."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "There is not a great deal of time between now and 2050. Only just over 30 years which represents just over 6 budget cycles. With the\ntarget to be zero carbon by 2050, there does not appear to be significant time or opportunity to be changing budgets. Also,\ninevitably, any carbon that is not offset through policy, must simply be offset through tree planting. So, the penalty for not meeting\n\nthe target is simply cost (i.e. spending more money on planting trees). This does not seem a particularly onerous penalty."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, I think the Trump era has demonised experts but they are still the best option for advising the government (who are often not\nexperts), or the public."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There are plenty of examples from around the world that could be used and it is experts that could help us to understand what that\nlooks like for New Zealand and the most effective examples that may work for us."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I understand the need to work with businesses and industries, but I also think they need to understand that there is a cost involved\n\nwith doing the right thing. That in order to continue to have a licence to operate, they need to change with the times and change\nproduction processes and business practices. I understand that on an individual level, these are often people with small businesses,\n\nsmall land owners that may not make big profits, but that's why the government should be instrumental in helping these businesses\ntransition. I believe this is best achieved through engagement and making each of them understand the potential impacts of doing\nnothing (which are catastrophic) including the picture for future generations."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    }
  ]
}
